Guide to the Department of Religion Records, 1954-1978 UA.25.35.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Department of Religion records
1954-1978
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Department of Religion
UA.25.35.0001
2.5 Linear Feet
The Department of Religion Records, 1954-1978, contains materials relating to the activities and operation of the Department of Religion. The Department of Religion offers undergraduate and graduate level courses surrounding numerous aspects of religious study. The collection includes information relating to the management of both academic and administrative affairs and includes correspondence, committee meeting minutes, event planning materials, budgetary information and other documents that illustrate the development of the Religious Studies program as well as the functioning of the department during this time.
Provenance
Transfer, 1974-1984, 1992
Historical Note
In 1960, the existing graduate and undergraduate programs in religious studies at Duke University were consolidated into the Department of Religion under the provision of the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences. The Department of Religion offers an undergraduate major and minor in Religious Studies, M.A. in Religious Studies and a nationally regarded PhD. program. The Department of Religion studies major world religious traditions including Islam, Christianity, Judaism, Buddhism, Hinduism, Confucianism and Taoism. The department also offers courses examining the core philosophical notions and broader impacts of religion on human life. Prominent faculty from the department have included William H. Poteat, an influential scholar on the Post-Critical mode of thinking who served as department chairman from 1972-1978 and Thomas Langford who later served as dean of the Duke University Divinity School from 1971-1981 and as Provost from 1991-1994.
Collection Overview
The Department of Religion Records contains correspondence, committee meeting minutes and faculty recruitment and departmental budgetary information produced by the Department of Religion between 1954-1978. The collection also provides information on curriculum and course development, planning materials for events and speakers hosted by the department and information about proposals for new professorships including a faculty exchange program with the University of North Carolina-Chapel Hill. The Department of Religion Records also includes materials related to development of the Masters and PhD. programs including dissertation proposals and sample copies of PhD. examinations. The collection also contains copies of the departmental newspaper, Tower of Babel, and information related to two departmental self-studies conducted in 1965 and 1975.
Access Restrictions
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Religious education -- Study and teaching; Duke University. Department of Religion; Duke University. Department of Religion; Poteat, William H.; Langford, Thomas A.
- Ad Hoc Committee on Teaching for Graduate Students, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Budget-- Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Budget-- Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Budget-- Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Budget-- Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Budget-- Correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Budget-- Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Center for Christian Family Life Education (Proposed), 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Committees--general, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Course Descriptions (and Reviews), 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Course Material, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Dissertation Committees, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted until 2052
- Examinations (Samples), 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Faculty Exchange--University of North Carolina-Chapel Hill, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Graduate Studies in Religion--Executive Council, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Graduate Faculty--Executive Committee, 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Graduate Studies in Religion--Executive Council, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Graduate Studies in Religion--Executive Council, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Graduate Studies in Religion--Executive Council, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Graduate Studies in Religion--Executive Council, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Honors Program, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Henry B. Luce Grant, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Independent Study--applicant instructions, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Independent Study, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Independent Study, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Restricted until 2047
- Independent Study, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Restricted until 2048
- Independent Study, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Restricted until 2049
- Independent Study, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Majors, 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Memoranda, University others, 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Minutes, Correspondence--General, 1954-1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Minutes, Correspondence--General, 1957-1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Minutes, Correspondence--General, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Minutes, Correspondence--General, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Minutes, Correspondence--General, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Miscellaneous--Appreciation Plaque for James Henry Phillips, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Organizations/Events--American Academy of Religion, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Organizations/Events--Miscellanous Papers in "High God", 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Organizations/Events: 1964 Conference on the High God in Africa--Papers (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Organizations/Events: 1964 Conference on the High God in Africa--Papers (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Organizations/Events--Summer Seminar in Israel, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Organizations/Events--Symposium on Christian Origins, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Poteat, Wiiliam H-- personal correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Poteat, Wiilliam H--speaking engagements, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Program II, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Residential Life Committee (T. Langford, Chairman), 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Self-Study, Departmental, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Self-Study, Departmental, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Special Programs, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Summer Session, 1964-1974 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Visitor--interviews for faculty positions, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 29)